Welcome to our fourth
problem session.
We're going to be talking about binary
trees mostly today. We'll talk a little bit
about binary heaps, which is a topic we won't
cover until next Tuesday. But it will appear
in very small ways on your problem
set four, which will be due next Friday.
So I'm going to go over a little bit of that
material today. But it's mostly concern.
The subject material for today is mostly binary
trees, specifically being applied to set data
structures and sequence data structures. As
Professor Domain talked to you earlier this week.
But for now, actually
as of yesterday,
you've seen all of the data structures that
we're going to cover that will implement the set
interface and
the sequence interface.
Those nice tables that Professor Domain has been
showing you, those are now complete. We have
some data structures that are really good constant
time operations for some operations. So we might
choose them
for some applications.
And this week,
we've been describing to you trees which achieve
really pretty good for any type of query operation
on my sets or sequences. Pretty good meaning
logarithmic time, not quite constant. But
for our purposes, log n is, I mean, on your
computer,
practically, not asymptotically, but practically,
log n is going to be at most what on your
computer?
Something like 64.
Any input that you're operating on
with n machine words as your input,
you need to be able to address all of those
machine words in your input. And on your computer,
the size of your machine word addresses 64 bits.
And we assume that the word size is at least log
in the size of your input
so that you can address the input.
So for your purposes,
on your computer,
log n is going to be no more than 64, which means
you get maybe a 50 times overhead. Or for smaller
instances, it could be more like 10 if you've
got 1 ,000 things that you're working on.
It's not that bad. It's
not a constant factor. For theory purposes.
But for your purposes, log n is much better
than a polynomial factor, another factor of n.
OK, so you've seen all the code. You've seen
implementations of all of these sets and sequence
interfaces.
So I went ahead and wrote a little. I compiled
all of that code from your recitation notes of all
of the different interface implementations. And
what I did was I wrote a little test program
to see how they
ran on a real machine.
So I have a
little test code here.
So I have a little folder
that lists an array implementing a sequence, a
binary tree implementing a sequence, a dynamic array
implementing a sequence, all these kinds of things.
Then set things, a sorted array being a set,
and a binary tree and a hash table. These
are our implementations. I'm not using Python
dictionaries for hash tables. I'm using the
implementations that are in your recitation.
And I'm going to run this little test efficiency
Python code that basically is just going to, for
each one, it's going to do a bunch of these
different operations and measure to see how much time
it took. I'm just logging how much time it
took. It's not an asymptotic analysis,
but hopefully
we see some separation.
So I'm going to press that. It runs a bunch
of tests. So let's take a look.
OK, so I got a bunch of sequence
operations.
And we got build, set at, get at,
insert, delete at the various places.
And I'm giving
these are the actual timings to some scale,
to some resolution that I had for these data
structures. And you can see build actually built
on this machine. Just allocating some array and
clearing it is a really efficient thing that
Python's going to do for me. And so that's
actually it's mislabeling that as log n.
But these other things, get at and set at,
really, really fast. That's constant time.
And then these other things, I essentially can't
do better than loop through the thing. And so it
takes linear time.
And again, sequence stuff,
setting at and getting at is slow.
But deleting and removing from the first
thing, I'm just relinking the pointer.
Dynamic arrays, again, set at, get at is fast
because it's just dynamic. It's just regular arrays.
And then inserting and deleting last, that's
getting me essentially constant time. Now, I'm
actually, when I'm running these tests to deal
with averages, I'm actually running these things a
lot of times and testing their performance. And
so I'm not seeing the worst case happen here. I'm
averaging over all of the things, which is
exactly what amortization means.
And so that's why
I'm getting good performance here.
A hash table, again, really,
oh, so this is what we
talked about in problem session last week,
implementing a double
-ended queue with a hash table.
This is that implementation. I just want to show
it to you. But it's actually pretty good. This is
what JavaScript uses for arrays.
And then a binary sequence represented as a
binary tree,
a balanced binary tree.
This is our AVL code that I had.
And all the other things have been really
pretty bad at insert at and delete at.
But this one does comparable to all the other
things. Now, you see these are a little bit more
machine cycles than
the other things, but not so bad, actually.
And then on the set side of things, again,
we had a sorted array.
Sorry, this
is a set from an array, basically.
It's an unsorted array. I'm just looking
for all the things. That's very bad times.
Array does these fine operations great, but
inserting and deleting is poor. That's why we need
binary trees. Hash tables get good kind of dictionary
operations, but really bad order operations.
And then the binary search tree, a set binary tree,
again, does quite good on all of these things.
In fact, it's getting
really quite good.
It's getting better for some reason than these.
The sorted array even did. So I don't know why
our implementations are not optimized at all, but
it does pretty well asymptotically. Yeah? Could
you explain again why in the first data
surgery we looked at, the build time was log n?
Well,
this is just labeled based off the timings,
right? It happens to be that probably there's a
C intrinsic underneath Python that allocates this
thing, and so it does it really fast. And so my
program that's looking at these numbers and trying
to guess what the asymptotic running time is, these
are just labels based on these things, ranges.
It's mischaracterizing. Actually, it's all
doing it at any time.
Yeah, well, I mean, in actuality, if it was
C code, right, if all of this stuff was in C,
probably we'd see that bar be longer because it's
actually having to go through and touch all that
memory. It's
still doing that here,
but all the Python stuff is super crufty, right?
It's like 100 times slower than anything that C
does. And so you're seeing
that disparity here. Does that make sense?
Okay, so I just wanted
to show you that.
We might release this for you to play around with,
but I just wanted to give you a taste of that.
Okay, any questions before
we move on?
How do I turn this off? Up
and off.
Shut down.
Yes.
Okay, so moving on to
problems, working some problems.
So you have your set of problems here. The first
one is we're going to look at a sequence AVL tree.
This is a sequence AVL tree. How do I know
that?
You don't necessarily, but
these things are certainly not in sorted order
of the things I'm storing in them, right?
So it better not be a set AVL tree, right? Is
it an AVL tree? Is it balanced? High balanced?
Yeah, basically. Actually, if you
compute the size of each subtree, right,
the left and right subtrees on all of these, you
can confirm for yourself, are balanced, right?
They're within plus or minus one of each other.
Actually, this is about as far away from balance as
you could get for this many nodes
while still maintaining height balance,
which is why this is an instructive
example. It's kind of at the limit.
Okay, and
what am I going to do? What's missing in this
picture if I'm claiming this is a sequence AVL tree?
Any ideas?
What's missing? What does the sequence AVL tree
store that I'm not showing in this picture?
What?
Counts and?
Heights, right?
So sequence AVL trees different than set AVL trees
are augmented by two things, right? Because I
need to be maintaining balance during
rotations, and so I need to store heights.
I need to be able to tell what the heights of these
subtrees are in constant time when I'm walking
up the tree fixing things.
And the sequence requires me to store their
subtree, the numbers there, right?
So I don't know. I'm not going to draw it for all
of these things. But how about for number four?
What's its height?
1, 2, 3, that's the longest path from the root
subtree of that. So this is height equals 3.
That came from height
equals 2 and height equals 1.
Does everyone see that? Yeah? And then the
size here, how big is that?
That's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, right?
So this is going to put size equals 7 here,
right? And that's coming from this guy, 1,
2, 3, 4. And this guy is 2,
right? So
how do I compute the subtree size?
It's my left subtree size plus my right subtree
size plus 1, right? And my height is taking the max
of the 2 plus 1, right?
All right, so we did all that yesterday.
So I'm just labeling these things. And what I'm
asking of you is to perform a delete operation.
This is a sequence tree.
So I'm finding things by their index in the tree,
right? So I'm going to ask you to delete the 8
thing in my sequence,
OK? So what is the 8 thing in my sequence?
Yeah? Just to clarify, so delete 8 is not delete
the number 8? Correct. Well, delete at 8. Do you
see that? It's a sequence operation. So it's in
the same position, not the other way. Yeah, so this
is very important that you differentiate between
sequence and set semantics, right? If I'm dealing
with the sequence,
I better not be looking up intrinsic things on
this data structure, right? Because it's not an
intrinsic data structure. It doesn't
support that. So if I wanted to support
find the, say, the index
of key 8 or something like that, right,
then all I could do is it's similar to an array.
I would just have to loop through the whole
sequence
and tell me if the thing's in there, right?
Can't really do better than linear time. This data
structure is not designed for that. What is it
designed for? It's designed to find things
by their index in the sequence, right? So
how do I find the 8th index?
Well, I mean, I'm looking at the tree. And I can
just count along the inorder traversal. What's the
inorder traversal, right?
0. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. OK, found 8. But
what does a sequence AVL tree do,
right?
I'm storing subtree sizes. And when I'm
here, I don't know what index I'm at, right?
How can I find out what index I'm at from the root?
I look at my left subtree, see how many it is,
right? There
are seven things here.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
8.
Right, yeah, because I'm looking for the 9th item
by index 8, right? So this is saying that I'm the
8th item, right?
I'm the guy at index 7.
Does that make sense? Because I'm
looking at the subtree size here.
So what do I know? I know that the
index that I'm looking for is to my right,
right? So I go down over here.
And I happen to know what
index of am I looking for in this subtree?
0, right? I want
the first thing in this subtree.
My search index has changed now, right? Because I
essentially dealt with all of those eight items,
right? So here, I'm looking for the 0 thing
in my index.
I look to my left. If I didn't have a left
subtree, I would be the 0 thing, right? And I would
return me. But there is stuff in here. So
I'm looking for the 0 thing in here, right?
Which is just him, and I return it, OK? And
actually, what I'm doing is I'm deleting it, right?
So I delete it.
Yuck.
What's the problem here?
I'm not height
balanced. What's not height balanced here?
The left subtree is ..
So this guy is not height balanced, right?
This guy's subtree is not height balanced,
right? This guy's 2. This guy's 1, OK?
So how do we fix it?
Rotate. JASON KUO - We
do some rotations, right?
This is actually the bad case, the third bad case
that we talked about yesterday, right? If I tried
to just left rotate this guy, what would it
look like?
It would put 12 here. It would put 10 here.
And 8 would be attached to that.
No, it's height balance wrong in the other
direction, right? That's no good, right?
So the way to handle this
case where I am badly skewed to the right,
but my right subtree is skewed
to the left, I have to do a rotation here,
right rotation, and
then do a rotation. So that's the formula,
OK? So here, we first do a right rotation at 10,
which gives me something that looks like 8, 10.
OK?
Now, obviously, this is
not better
than what was before, but it's an intermediate
step so that we can fix it, right?
We right rotate
here, and then we left rotate here, right?
The default is that we would left
rotate here, but because this had
the skew in the wrong direction,
I need to right rotate this one first, and then
we can do it. So now I rotate all of these guys
over, right?
And put 12 down here,
8 here, 10 here.
Done.
Everyone
see that that's what a rotation looks like?
OK, it takes a little while to get your mind
wrapped around what the transformation is, but
hopefully you guys all followed that transformation.
There was a little magic while I was trying to
draw. Yeah? I still don't feel like this
tree is height balance. JASON KUO - It's not.
Good observation. Why is that? This thing still
has height 3. What is the height of this thing?
1, right? This is height 1. And
actually, when I was doing that rotation,
I needed to update all these augmentations,
right?
Which augmentations did I really need to? Which
subtrees have changed during those things?
I don't remember what the thing looked
like. What did the thing look like? 10
had 8 in its subtree,
so its subtree definitely changed. Right?
8 subtree changed. But all of
them changed. JASON KUO - 12 didn't change,
eventually. These had 10 and 8.
And now it has none. JASON KUO - OK, so there's
the case analysis that's in your lecture notes and
was done in recitation. It
tells you that these ABCD kind of subtrees,
the ones
that could change in these things,
those subtrees don't change. The only subtrees
that change during one of these fixed operations,
when you do
one or two rotations,
is either two nodes or three nodes
whose subtree has changed. Here,
it could have been the case that
three subtrees have changed, right?
But in the easy case, only two nodes, x and y,
I think, in the nodes could have changed. And so
when I do that, I have
to recompute
their augmentations
from their augmentations of their children.
But it's only a constant number of those, so I
just recompute them because the subtrees below me
haven't changed.
Right? OK, so we have
a height mismatch here.
I think this is kind of why the 12 doesn't change.
12 used to be where 8 is when we had two kids, 7
and 10. So originally, in the picture, 12 has a
bunch of things in its subtree, right? 10 and 8.
And we just deleted 7. Right?
So its subtree definitely changed. There used to
be three. 7 did not change. JASON KUO - Oh, no,
no, no. Sorry. It did. Right? Yeah.
So here, three node subtrees have changed.
But that's actually the most. I'm
showing you the worst case. Right?
Only three nodes possible in doing one of these
double rotation things could have changed their
subtrees. And so we just have to
fix the augmentation of those three things.
In the easy case, it's just two things. OK? All
right. We have an unbalance. How can we fix this?
I could have been mean. Right?
I want to be able
to right rotate here. Right? To rebalance.
I could have been mean
and switched these two.
Right?
If I switch those two, then I'd have to do two
rotations to fix this thing because the middle one
is heavier than
the left one against what I'm doing. Right?
But I'm not that mean. So I'm going
to right rotate. How do I do that?
Well, right rotate at 6 is going
to bring all of this down below 4. Right?
And stick this subtree as
the left child of 6. Does that make sense?
Yuck. That's
going to be fun to draw.
I'm just going to redraw it.
That makes more sense. Right?
4, 11, 3, 2, 1. And then 6,
5.
9, 8, 12,
10.
That's the right rotation at 6.
Is everyone cool with this?
The rotation, my x is 6.
My y is 4. Right? I have a, b, c subtrees.
Right? What I'm doing is kind of switching
which of x and y is the root here. Right?
So now y is the root.
And b and c subtrees here now become the children
of x underneath y. And notice that, hopefully,
through all that process,
my in -order traversal has not changed.
We had to update our augmentations along the way.
But it's a constant every time we walk up the
tree. And we walk up the tree only
a logarithmic number of times. Yeah? Yes?
Every time we do a rotation, we just update the
augmentation immediately afterward before we do any
other rotation. Exactly.
Yeah. Second part.
Updating the augmentation just means
updating the count and the height,
just the properties that stay. Yeah.
Basically, what we did, when we augmented,
Professor Domain yesterday defined
for you what a subtree property is. Right?
It meant a property that I
can compute only by looking at my children,
the augmentations of my
children.
So here,
instead of trying to increment or try to think
about locally what this augmentation should be,
I'm going to throw away my old augmentation and
just recompute it from my children, because those,
recursively, better be
correct. Does that make sense? Yeah?
So just looking at how the rotation works, right,
I'm going to pull the wrap in my head around.
So basically, you're swapping 4 and
6. And that way, 4 becomes the parent node,
and 6 becomes the right node.
I'm going to draw this picture.
It's just
something you've got to memorize.
It's x, b, c, and a. Can
you see that picture?
Already down. What? Already down. Yeah. It's in
your notes. It's not a big deal. Right? But if
you've got this structure
where x has a left child,
and these subtrees may be empty or not, doesn't
really matter, what I can do is I can move from
here to there,
has the same in -order traversal order, but
it's got a different shape. And in
particular, subtree heights have changed,
which means it can help us rebalance the tree.
And that's the whole point of ABL. Does that make
sense? And that's the right rotation. This one
is a right rotation. This is a left rotation.
Any other questions?
Yeah? So for updating the object rotation, so how
many nodes do you have to update back in? So just
the other ancestors? So
as I'm walking up the tree,
every node I might have to fix with the rebalance.
But that rebalance does at most two rotations.
And there's at most log and ancestors that I
have, because my tree is height balanced, right?
At 2 log
n or something like that, right?
Which means that at max, I might have to do four
log n rotations, right? Because each one could
do two rotations.
Does that make sense?
Now, in actuality, you can prove that in a
delete operation,
it's possible that you have to do a logarithmic
number of these rotations up the tree. This was
that bad case.
The original
tree I gave you is called a Fibonacci tree.
This height
balance tree you can have on a given number
of nodes,
that's the fewest nodes for a certain height. You
can think of it either way. And if you generalize
that to a large enough thing, then that thing will
take a logarithmic number of rotations going up.
Now, actually, with an insertion, you can actually
prove. You can go through the case analysis.
An insertion operation
will always rebalance the tree after 1.
After 1 rebalance operation, which could
include 2 rotations. Does that make sense?
Yeah? So in right rotation, you become the
right child of your previous left child, right?
Yeah. So in right rotation, this guy becomes a
right child. Yeah. So can you not rotation that you
can't perform depending on whether you have a
child? Yeah. So if I didn't have a left subtree,
I can't
perform a rotation, a right rotation. Yeah.
So a right rotation necessitates that I have a
left child. So if you're doing it, and you'll see
our code actually
checks to make sure you have a left child,
that's an assertion that you might want to
fire before you ever do one of these rotations.
Anything else? Yeah? Just to reiterate, so an
insertion may take 2 rotations at most to fix?
A constant number of rotations in the deletion
could take a logarithmic number. Rotations.
Now, that's not something you need to know.
It's not something I'm proving here to you.
Just something that's
interesting. There are rebalancing schemes,
like in CLRS. They introduce a red
-black tree to introduce balance.
And those trees actually have a weaker bound on.
It's not as tightly height balanced as an AVL tree
is. It
allows higher than skew 2. Right?
And because it's kind of a weaker restriction,
they get away with only doing a constant number of
rotations.
They can afford that before they fix
the tree, but a little more complicated.
Just by the .. JASON
KUO - Very nice. OK, any questions on this?
OK, so this is more of a mechanical
question you'll get on your problem sets.
So we're going to go into the theory -type
questions.
These
are going to be reduction -type questions.
OK, so this first problem,
Fick -Nurrie.
This is anyone? Nick
Fury, right. So it's an Avengers reference.
So basically, what happens in this thing, he's got
a list of superheroes that each have an opinion
on whether they
should go fight Sanos.
OK,
and their opinion can
be strongly positive or strongly negative.
And so what Fick is trying to do is find from
among his Revengers what the log -N most extreme
opinion Revengers are so that he can talk to them.
He doesn't want to talk to everybody. He wants
to talk to a logarithmic number of
them. OK, it's kind of whatever. All right,
so basically, we have
a classified
situation where you're given as a read -only
input data store of these things in an array. OK,
and I want to find the log -N ones with the
strongest opinions. Does that make sense?
And I want to do it, and the first problem
is in linear time.
OK, so
you actually don't know how to do this yet.
You'll know how to do it with material that
you cover in,
well, they teach you one way to do it in 046,
but we're not going to get you there right now.
We'll
teach you another way to do it on Tuesday,
which is via binary heaps.
Binary heaps are an interesting thing that
implements a subset of the set interface. OK,
really, it's just you can build
on some iterable x. OK,
I collect a bunch of things. These items have
keys. It's a keyed data structure in the same way.
It's implementing what we call a priority
queue interface. I can build these things.
I can insert things, but I'm not going to do
that here. All I really need here for this
situation is a delete superlative kind
of operation, in this case, probably max.
Delete max.
OK, so this is like I
got a data structure.
I'm calling these things. Does that make sense?
Yeah. What's a priority queue? JASON KUO - Yes, a
priority queue is essentially
something that implements these two things.
Actually, there's
a third one where I can insert a new thing,
but I'm not going to need that right now. So that's
what a priority queue is. And actually, a set,
this is a subset
of the set interface.
The nice thing about a
heap, which I won't show you how it's done,
but what a heap can do. So if I had both of these
operations implemented using a set AVL tree,
how long would
these things take me?
How long does
it take to build a set?
JASON KUO - AVL tree.
N log n, right? Because essentially, I'm getting
a sorted order out of this thing if I'm inserting
these things one at a time.
Or I could sort them and then put them in a tree
in linear time, like you saw a couple of days ago
in recitation.
But I
have to sort them at some point.
I
need to take at least n log n time, because
if I'm going to be able to return there
order, their traversal order in linear time,
and I have this lower bound of n log n on sorting,
I kind of needed to spend n log n time here.
And how long would
this delete max take?
It's sorted so log n. JASON KUO - Log n, right?
So it's a set AVL tree. Where is my max? It's the
rightmost thing. I can just walk down the
thing, take it off. Maybe I have to rebalance.
But that's a log n operation. So
the same as insert last in my subtree.
JASON KUO - So for a set AVL tree, this is
n log n. This
is log n, right?
Now,
there's another data structure that does better
for one of these operations, and the same for the
other one that
we've learned earlier.
Anyone remember?
Set AVL tree didn't actually give us anything
over a sorted array in a dynamic array, OK?
JASON KUO - Was we have a,
we could sort it in n log n time
using merge sort or something like that.
And then we could just pop off the last one
n times, right?
That would be
an amortize. I mean, if I didn't care about
taking up that size, I could do it in worst case,
constant time. I just read off the last one. I
don't need to resize the array ever, right?
I can just ignore that. Does that make sense?
OK. But that's, OK. If
I had a data structure
that implemented to these two operations, can
someone tell me an algorithm to generate fixed list?
Don't worry about running time right now,
but that just uses these two operations.
Yeah.
So we built this data structure.
JASON KUO - Mm -hmm. It's ordered from least to
greatest for absolute value. JASON KUO - So don't
worry about
where things are ordered or anything like that. I
don't tell you how these things are implemented,
right? All I'm saying is I can accept a bunch of
these things, and I can remove the maximum and
return it,
OK? Yeah, but anyways, just build it. Make sure
that you build it such that the opinion levels are
the absolute value of the opinion levels. JASON
KUO - Sure. OK. So that's a nice thing. What I'm
going to do, as your colleague is saying, is I'm
going to look through all of the things in my
input. I'm going to copy
it over to some writable memory. Store, OK?
That read -only thing is not relevant to this part
of the problem, right? What I'm going to do is,
right.
Sorry. I'm thinking about your problem set that
we're writing and mixing it up. OK. So we copy it
over to our new bit
of linear size array,
but instead of putting their values there, I'm
going to put the absolute values of their values.
Does that make sense? I just check if it's
negative. If it is, I put the positive thing there,
right?
OK? JASON KUO -
And then I stick that array in
this build, right? I put that there, right?
So that'll take some whatever this
build time is. And then I
can delete max k times, or I can delete max
some number of times,
however many things that I need,
right?
So if I have a set of these things, I can
just do that log n times, right? So for this,
if I had such a data structure, I could do
this in one run of this operation and log n
runs of this operation. Does that make sense?
I can solve this problem reducing to this data
structure, right?
Now, for a sorted array or a set AVL tree,
right, this operation kind of kills
me already. It takes n log n time, right?
And what it
does is
it does this operation in linear time. You
will see
that on Tuesday. And it does this operation
in log n time,
OK?
So what's the running time if I use a binary
heap to implement this data structure?
Order of n times order
log n times log n. How big is log n squared
log squared n compared to n? It's smaller,
right?
So if I add those two running times
together, it's still linear, right?
OK,
so that's how you solve the first problem,
OK? I didn't have to tell you what a binary heap
was or how it did what it did. All I needed to
tell you was that it did this operation in linear
time, and it did this operation in log n time,
OK?
Yeah? All right.
The magic will be shown to you on Tuesday.
Part B says, now suppose fixed computer is
only allowed to write to at most log n space.
Well, OK, that's a problem
here, right? Because before, we copied over
the entire array,
filtered it out, right,
and then did some operations. But we couldn't even
afford this if we couldn't store the whole thing
externally in
writable memory, right?
OK, so we can't do that. So in some sense,
this is a more restrictive environment, right?
I
can do less things than I could.
It's less powerful than my previous situation,
where I had as much space as I wanted to use, right?
So it kind of makes sense
that I maybe couldn't get
the running time bound that we had before,
right?
Because I'm in a more
restrictive computational setting, right?
OK,
now this is something you could solve with binary
heaps, but you don't have to. You could solve it
with set AVL trees.
Does anyone have an idea of how
you could solve this using a set AVL tree?
I'm limited by my
number of my space is at most log n. Yeah?
So how much space does a set AVL
tree take? JASON KUO - Right, space, right?
There's constant number of pointers for each one
of these nodes, right? And I'm storing in nodes
and space, right? Basically,
every data structure we've shown you
takes space the order of the things that we're
storing, right? It's not using additional space. It
might take more time to do certain things,
but the space
takes the number
of items that we're storing
plus maybe a constant factor, right?
So I'm going to draw my input
here, which I can only read. I can't write.
Do I give it a? I'm just going to call it a. OK,
so this is my list of all the revenger opinions.
OK, I can only read it.
But my computer can only
write to this log rhythmic amount of space.
What can I put in that space?
The log n greatest. JASON KUO - Well, I can
certainly put log n things in there. OK,
so if I'm given that restriction, I probably want
to build a data structure of that size, right?
You know, containing that number of things.
That make sense?
Because what else are
you going to do? Right?
OK, so I gave you an idea.
Maybe we could use a set AVL here, right? I
see a logarithm in my answer, right?
It's very possible that we might have sorted arrays
or set AVL things. Those things give me a log
somewhere in
my running times, right?
So it kind of makes sense that I might have
maybe a set AVL tree here.
That would be helpful for me.
Yeah?
Because it's sorted and you have the traversal
order, you can calculate the traversal order and
insert things inside of it pretty easily. JASON
KUO - Sure. I can do all of those things. But in
particular, it's
going to help me be able to find
a large one quickly, right?
If I kind of have a set of things, it's going to
be. And I'm maintaining this data structure by
adding
things incrementally to it. Right?
I can find out what the biggest one is or the
smallest one pretty fast, right? In log n time.
Right? So if I have log n things in a tree
here, right? What's the height of that thing?
Log log n.
JASON KUO - Log log n. That looks familiar.
So what can
I afford? I can afford
a linear number
of set AVL tree operations on this
data structure, right?
You had a question?
I forgot. JASON KUO - OK. I'm sorry. Yeah?
For an AVL tree, does it have to
be a BTS tree? JASON KUO - It's BTS. BST.
Right? So when I talk about someone
who likes Korean K -pop. OK. So BST,
but in natural kind of in the lingo that you're
probably used to hearing in other contexts.
What we mean in this class
is a set AVL tree. Right?
So sometimes what people refer to as a binary
search tree doesn't have balanced semantics. Right?
So we might call in this
class a set binary tree. Right? But really,
they're useful because they're balanced. So we're
going to usually just assume that we're talking
about balanced things here.
Now, a set AVL tree has these binary search tree
semantics where the keys are ordered. These items
have keys and they're
ordered. It's a set interface. Right?
Whereas we
also presented to you a sequence interface
for which these things don't even have keys. How
could I store set semantics there? Right? But
that's the distinction that we
mean when we say binary search tree versus
really a set AVL tree versus . Yeah? So if we
were going to make an AVL tree out of this, would
that mean that when we make a node, we tell it we
are keying on the absolute value of the .. JASON
KUO
- OK. So when you're making a set AVL tree,
you've got to tell us what, if you're storing
objects, you've got to tell me what their key is.
Right? If you're just storing some numbers,
like what I'm doing here, right,
now this isn't a set AVL tree. Right? But if I'm
just storing numbers, I have to tell you the items
that I'm
storing are the keys. OK?
And then everything follows. Right? But if you've
got an object that you're trying to sort, like
the students in this room, you've got a lot
of properties. Right?
The people with phone number.
Right? Maybe I want to key you on phone number
for some reason. Maybe that's going to help
me find out where you live. I don't know. This
is going to be a little bit. I don't want to go
there. OK. So but if I give you a set AVL tree,
I've got to tell you what it's keyed on. If I give
you a sequence AVL tree, right,
it's obvious what my traversal order is going
to be because I'm giving you a sequence.
Right? That's what the input gate
was. Right? Does that make sense?
All right. So I've got this set AVL tree of
size log n.
What should it be keyed by?
Absolute value. JASON KUO - Absolute value of their
preference, right, or of their opinion. I don't
remember what this is called. But what log
n things do I put in here?
I don't know.
I don't know anything about these things.
What makes one better than another? Right?
Let's just put the first log n things. That
make sense?
All right. What could that
tell me? Now I've
put this thing in. How long did that take?
JASON KUO - Log n times
log log n time. Right?
But that's
much less than our running time. Right? So
that we're looking for. So I don't really care.
Right? I want you to say how long it took.
But for my purposes, I know that it's lower than
the running time I'm looking for. And I did that
operation once. I don't
really care about it anymore. OK?
Yep? How did you get log n times log n? JASON
KUO - Because the number of things I'm storing in
this thing is log n.
And so if I pattern match the build time of
an AVL tree and I stick log n in there, right,
then it's log
n times log log n. Gotcha. JASON KUO - OK.
How about one iteration? JASON KUO - Well,
right now, I've just built this thing. Right?
Maybe I just built it once.
I'm asserting to you
that maybe I don't need to build it again.
Right? What could I do instead? So right now,
I know I haven't filtered my data at all.
Right? I'm just storing these
things in sorted order in some way. Right?
What can I do
to maybe start processing
the rest of the data? Yeah?
Well, I think we could try to scroll through the
list A and try to find someone that's bigger than.
Try to keep the
maximum data. JASON KUO - Ah, kind of sweep
this guy over, inserting things,
and always maintaining.
If I do that and I keep sticking things in, I'll
have this sorted thing at the end. And now I can
just read off
the biggest k things. Right?
However, as
I'm inserting things across here,
my thing's growing. I'll just delete the smallest
one. JASON KUO - Oh, delete the smallest one. I
like that idea.
Right? So basically replace it. JASON KUO - Yeah,
basically replace it. Right? So what I'm going to
do, here's a proposal. We're going to take
the next guy, stick it in.
Awesome.
Which one
don't I care about now?
The smallest one
there. So kick the smallest one out.
Now, this one
that I stuck in may be the smallest. Right?
I passed it through
this thing. But how long did that take me?
Took me the height of this tree. What's
the height of this tree? Log log n. Right?
So I put one in.
I pop one out. That's the smallest. Right?
And I keep doing that all the way down the thing.
How long did that take me? JASON KUO - Oh, about
time .. JASON KUO - Yeah,
I'm processing n minus
log n things, which is basically n. Right?
And each one of those
operations took me height of the tree time.
So that gives me the running time
that we're looking for, n log log n.
Yeah? Is this like running this with a sliding
window technique? JASON KUO - Yeah, it's kind of a
sliding window technique. You may have been
using one recently.
OK, everyone OK with this?
Yeah? Can you just remind
me of the context that we're talking about?
Log log n tree and where? JASON KUO - So this
thing, the size of this thing is log log n? Yeah.
JASON KUO - I mean, sorry, log n. And the
height of this thing is log of the size.
I'm sorry, but in
relation to our little log n size
right there, is it sticking this full of
small log log n trees? JASON KUO - No, sorry.
I'm taking this stuff.
There's no
intermediate data structure here.
I'm just sticking all these things into a
set AVO. JASON KUO - Into one set AVO. OK.
JASON KUO - Of size log n.
I'm sticking a guy in,
popping the worst guy out.
Going through all the things. I need to make sure
when I'm sticking it in, I'm keeping track of
which revenger it is and that I'm taking the
absolute value and all those nitty gritty kind of
things. But
that's the basic idea.
I'm just taking this.
I'm sliding the window in,
putting something in, taking something out that
may or may not probably is not the same thing.
And at the end of this procedure, the
invariant I'm maintaining here is that my thing
always has the k
largest opinions of the ones that I've processed
so far. That's obviously true at the beginning
when I build this thing. And when I
get to the end, I processed all the things.
It has log n. And so I have the
log n largest, highest extremist opinions.
And then I can just do an inner traversal of
this thing and return. Does that make sense?
And I've only
used logarithmic space.
OK? Yeah? So I don't get
it. Are all the opinions in that AVL tree?
JASON KUO - Are all the opinions in that AVL tree?
JASON KUO - All of these opinions are in the AVL
tree. And at some point, I will insert
every opinion into this AVL tree. But I'll
be removing the ones that I don't care about as I
go. Does that make sense? I'm always maintaining
the invariant
that this thing, before I insert something,
has exactly log n items in it. And then I'm
maintaining that invariant by sticking one in, taking
one out. Oh, OK. So then which one are you
believing?
JASON KUO - Always the min, right? Because I'm
wanting the largest ones. And the min by absolute
value? So
I'm keying by the absolute value of these
opinions. Yeah? OK. So then total runtime ..
JASON KUO - Total runtime here, right? It's
bookkeeping, right? So it took me log n times log log n
time to build this data
structure at the beginning, right?
Plus n times log
log n. I did basically n operation asymptotically,
n operations this way. It's actually n minus log
n operations, right? And each one of those
operations, tree operations,
doing one insert, one delete, each one
of those took the height of the tree time.
And so this is that. Good?
Yeah? If instead of one, we just
insert and delete, if you do a comparison,
and then? JASON KUO -
So inserting and deleting,
a set AVL tree is actually doing comparisons within
its data structure. Just compare with the min.
JASON KUO - Sure, you could do that. Right? So I
could do it the other way, right? I could remove
the smallest element here to start
with.
And then I compare it with this guy, and then
which ever is bigger, I stick it back in.
Same thing, right?
It's just am I doing the delete first, and then
the insertion, or I'm doing the insertion first,
and then the deletion?
Any other questions?
Lots of questions. All right. Well, I'm
probably going to have to skip the problem.
We're going to move on to
SCLR. All right. What's the reference here?
Yeah, CLRS.
JASON KUO - OK. So these are four academics who
wrote a popular textbook in computer science.
OK. This is
the same kind of K kind of thing.
OK. They found K first editions,
and they want to auction them off.
People can go onto their website. They
have a bidder ID. It's a unique identifier.
And they can place a bid
for one of these books.
And they can change it during the bidding
period. But at the end of the bidding period,
the academics want to know what
is the expected revenue I'll get by selling to
the K highest bidders. Does that make sense?
Yeah?
OK. So note that before I build this data structure,
I know what K is. K is a fixed thing, right?
Because my running time of this get revenue depends
on this K. It's not an input to that operation,
right?
So K is kind of, I don't know what it is a
priori. It could be n over 2. It could be log n,
right? It could be 1, right?
But the data structure I build needs to satisfy
these running time properties no matter what choice
of K that the academics told me. Does that
make sense?
OK. So what I need to
do is, as time is going on, people are placing
new bids and updating their bids, right? And
those updates can take log
n time. But as soon as I close the window,
I want to be able to tell in constant time
what
the K highest bidders are.
Any ideas on how to do this? What are
the operations that I have to do? I have
to be able to place a new bid.
Right? I associated with a bidder is an ID
and a bid, which is also an integer, right? How
many dollars I'm going to pay for this book.
Update the bid. In some sense, I need to find
whether that person placed the bid before, right,
in my data structure. So at some point, I'm going
to need to find on bidder ID. Does that seem
plausible, right? So I might want to have some
kind of dictionary on bidder IDs. Right? When I say
that I want to have a dictionary on something,
right, I'm not specifying to you yet
how I'm going to implement
that dictionary. What are my usual options?
Hash
table. But what if I need worst case time?
A set AVL tree, right? That's going
to be your go -to for a dictionary,
right? Because that's going to give me
log n time to find things by a key, right?
You could also use a sorted array, right? But
that's going to not be dynamic. And here, we're
updating who's in my data structure all the time,
right? People are going in and placing bids,
right? New people placing bids. So my set of things
that I care about is changing all the time. So
that's probably going to steer me away from sorted
arrays because they're not good with dynamic
operations.
OK. So I'm going to
need some kind of dictionary on bidder IDs.
But I'm also going to need to maintain the sum
of the k highest bidders. Does that make sense?
And so in some sense, I need to keep track
of
an ordered notion of
the bidders, right, the bids that are
in my data structure. Does that make sense?
So order is going to be important on the bids.
I'm going to need to look up on bidder ID.
And that's about it, right?
OK, yeah? Just checking. So if something
that's worst case runs at worst case time
runs at an expected that's
the amount of time, but not vice versa?
Yeah, so that's a very good observation, right?
If it runs in worst case time, it also runs an
expected that time, right? Because there's
essentially no randomization that I'm talking about
here, right? Or if it's worst case, it runs
at worst case time.
So there's a stronger notion, which we want
you to specify,
which that actually there is no randomization
here. We're not using a hash table,
right, in this class. Really, that's the only
situation where that's going to be an issue, right?
But if it is, what this problem is saying for each
object state, whether your running time is worst
case expected and or amortized, what we're really
trying to get you to say is, what's the how?
Evaluate the running time of your algorithm
with the proper qualifications, right?
If it took worst case,
I want you to say that it took worst case.
If you used a hash table, I want you to say
expected.
And if
these operations were sometimes really bad,
but on average, they're really good if I
did a lot of them, that's amortized, right?
Or if I reduced to
using a dynamic array,
right? Or if I reduced to using a hash table,
those dynamic operations would still be amortized,
right? OK,
so the dynamic ones.
Nice thing about linked data structures is that
dynamic operations aren't amortized, right? So
we're going to be able to get one. Now, for this
problem, we can actually get worst case bounds. So
we're going to try for that.
You can also do it in expected using some
hash tables for that dictionary, right? OK,
so when you approach a
data structures problem in this class,
you want to tell me what
it is you're storing, first off. Right?
Tell me what's supposed
to be in those things,
right? Some invariants on this data structure
to make sure that when I do queries later,
that these things are being maintained, right?
So that if I have, you know, if I'm maintaining a
sorted array, right, and I'm supporting an
operation to find the maximum,
I better, anything I do to this data structure,
better be maintaining the invariants that these
things are in sorted order so the last thing has
the maximum item because my max return thing is
going to look there and
return that. Does that make sense?
So I want to tell you, you want to tell me what
is being stored at a generic point in time during
your data structure, right? What is being maintained
so that when I support a dynamic operation or
a query, right, in a dynamic operation where I'm
inserting and deleting things from this thing,
I need to make
sure that I'm maintaining those invariants.
And when I'm querying, I can actually rely
on those invariants
to answer my query.
Does that make sense?
OK. So for this problem, this is
4, 3.
OK.
Any ideas?
I have two kind of keys that I might have to
deal with. One's a bid ID and one's a bid, right?
So how could
I, if I have two keys,
right, that I might want to
maybe order on one and look up on another,
how many data structures
do you think I'm going to use?
Two. That's a pretty good guess. OK. So one
of them,
let's just guess, right?
Like, I need to be able to look up on bid,
right? So let's store
these bidders,
right,
in some kind of dictionary that's going to be able
to look up those things fast, right? So two data
structures, right? One
is a dictionary on keyed on bidder ID. OK?
What else am I going to want?
What's up?
The other way around,
a dictionary stored on the bids.
Is a dictionary what I want here? I think
that I'll be upset at maybe all the time.
I want to maintain order somehow,
right? Because I want to maintain the k
biggest things that I've
seen so far, right? Now,
if I have, at some point in time, right, what's
going to happen, right? If I'm maintaining the k
largest at any point in time, it's possible that
one of those bidders maybe decreases his bid,
right? So it's no
longer in the highest.
I'm going to also need to keep track of the other
guys to see who I should add back into that set,
for example, right?
So here's an idea.
I'm going to keep not just one other data structure,
but two other data structures. Maybe this is a
leap.
You don't have to do this.
There's a way to do it with just one other.
But I'm going to store two more.
One is a kind of a data structure to store.
So I'm going
to store bidders with store
the k highest bidders and a data structure
to store the n minus k highest bidders.
Does that make sense?
So this separates my problem quite nicely,
right?
Every time someone does
an interaction with this data structure, I
can check to see whether it's bigger
than the smallest thing in here, right?
If it is, I can do
the same kind of trick I did before, right?
I can remove it and
stick my new one in there, right?
But I removed it. I can maintain this property,
right? So I stick it in here, right? There's
another case.
What's the other case?
It's smaller, right?
In which case, I don't do anything to this data
structure, and I just stick it into here. Does that
make sense?
So what are the operations these
data structures need to maintain?
Finding the minimum or the maximum of these
two sets. Does that make sense?
I don't have those operations. I don't have
them anymore.
But they were the priority queue operations.
They had delete max, right? And also insert
were things that it
did well on, right? So any priority queue,
right? Anything that can
deal with maxes and mins, right,
is good, right? And what's a data structure you
know that can deal with maxes and mins pretty
efficiently?
The set ADL, right?
So instead of data structure here,
I'm going to say set AVL.
And obviously, it's going to
be keyed by bid, right? Because that's the thing
that I'm going to want to find maxes and mins
over.
OK? Everyone following the logic
here of why I'm maintaining these things?
And invariance that I want to
maintain because when I go to, for example,
do this query, get revenue,
right, I can just run through and sum all of
these things. Oh, wait. How much time do I have?
Do I have
k time? No, I don't have k time.
So I can't afford to sum up all of these things
at the end of my query. I have to return it to you
in constant time. Any ideas?
Yeah,
just compute,
update a
sum, right? Along with this data structure,
I'm going
to keep a fourth thing,
which is just total of their
bids, right? I'm going to call it like a t,
OK?
And that's something I'm maintaining. It's part of
my data structure, right? You can think of it as
I'm
augmenting this thing with a number, right?
And the point of augmenting this thing with a number
is that I can just, if I need to know what the
total of this stuff is, I can just
look at that number. Does that make sense?
All right. So now I think we're almost done.
We're basically done, right? How do we do this?
Someone walk through to me how I
would
get revenue
with this data structure.
I basically kind of told you, look at this
number, return it,
right? Because
that's the invariance that I've maintained
on my data structure. I'm relying on this invariant.
Now, I better make sure this is good when I do
dynamic operations, right? I make
sure I maintain it. But if I, by induction,
are ensured that all of this stuff is good, and
when I do a dynamic operation, all that stuff is
maintained,
then I'm all good, right? So get revenue after
I kind of did all this. Extra work, right,
is very easy. I
just look at this number and return it, OK?
So when we're grading a data structure's
problem, usually we give you some points first
for setting up your data structure separately
from the operations. And then we give
you points per
operation that you successfully deal with,
and then some points for
correctness and running time. Yeah?
You had a question? So would total be like a
thing that we update whenever we mess around?
Like the highest bidder tree
and then the n minus k highest bidder tree?
Sorry, say that again? So are we treating the
total like to an augmentation that we update every
time we do something? Yeah, yeah. So it's just
one number. It's not really a data structure. It's
just one number that I'm
storing with my database, right?
OK?
All right,
so how do I implement a new bid operation?
Yeah?
Can we assume that the bids will also be unique?
Can you assume that the bids may be unique? No,
right? So that's actually something that is
a really useful observation.
We've been talking about set data
structures as requiring unique keys, right?
How can I deal with non -unique keys? It actually
turns out that hash table, it's really important
that these
be unique keys, right?
Because I need to check whether it's in there. I'm
looking for that single key. And when I find it,
I have to return, right? If I had multiple things
with that key, I might not return the one that
I'm looking for, right?
It doesn't even make sense, right?
But you can
generalize the set kind
of infrastructure, right, to deal with multisets.
How can I do that? Well, with each key,
right? Again, I'm storing unique keys. With each
key, I can link it to a sequence data structure
or any other
data structure, right?
And what I'm going to do is
I'm going to, anything that has that key,
I'm going to stick it
in that data structure,
right? So instead of storing one item there, I
have the possibility of storing many things there.
Now, I have to change the semantics here,
right? If I'm saying find on this key,
well, now I could say I'm going
to return all of the things with that key.
Or I'm going to store something with that key,
right? But you get the idea. All I have to do is map
it to
some other data structure to maintain those
things. But maybe.